Simon Andrew Purdue

Date of birth: 10 September 1992

Email: purdue.s@husky.neu.edu

RESEARCH INTERESTS

My research interests lie primarily in the realm of occupational health and industrial history, but extend to a broader range of historical social issues, primarily in the context of the late 19th and early 20th centuries. I see the next step in my research as being a more detailed study into occupational health, hopefully comparing the cases of heavily industrialized cities in the US with those in Ireland and Britain. I am also very interested in the links between gender and industry, and how women's roles in work and industry varied and developed across the nineteenth and twentieth centuries. My interests also extend to the rise and relative success of working class movements such as trades unions and friendly societies, and more broadly to urban and social history as a whole.

AWARDS AND SCHOLARSHIPS

Graduate Student Assistantship, Northeastern University 2016-2022

Wellcome Trust Humanities (Masters) Studentship 2015-16

As a result of my work at the undergraduate level and my potential for future research activity I was awarded the highly competitive Wellcome Trust's Humanities Masters Studentship for 2015-2016. This award, totalling €26000, sponsors a one year Masters program in the history of medicine, and is only awarded to students showing an intention 'to make a long-term academic career in the field'.¹

CONFERENCES AND PRESENTATIONS

Culture, Conflict and Commemoration: Reflections on Struggle and Resilience UCD School of History MA CONFERENCE 2016

I was heavily involved in the organisation, promotion and running of the UCD History Masters Conference in 2016. My role in this included devising the conference theme, designing and ordering the conference panels and designing promotional material for the event. I also presented a paper entitled 'Danger on the Docks: Occupational Health in the Belfast Shipbuilding Industry, 1870-1914'.

'Mode 1' Conference 2014

As part of my undergraduate degree I was responsible for the organisation and running of an academic conference, at which I also presented a paper, 'Bear ye One Another's Burdens: Belfast's Friendly Societies 1890-1910'.

¹ The Wellcome Trust, *Humanities and Social Science Funding Schemes- Master's Awards*, http://www.wellcome.ac.uk/Funding/Humanities-and-social-science/Funding-schemes/Masters-awards/index.htm, 10/07/2015, 1:12pm

EDUCATION & QUALIFICATIONS:

September 2016- PhD in World History

Northeastern University

September 2015-August 2016 MA in the Social and Cultural History of Medicine University College Dublin (Wellcome Trust Studentship)

September 2011-2015 BA (Hons.) (International) History

University College Dublin and Boston College

MA in the Social and Cultural History of Medicine

In the academic year 2015-2016 I will be undertaking a Masters degree in the history of medicine at UCD. The MA offers a combination of taught and research based elements, but is primarily a research degree, with the final dissertation comprising 60% of the total award. My proposed thesis hopes to explore the issue of occupational health among Belfast's women and children working in the city's booming textile industries between 1802 and 1914, examining the series of 'Factory Acts' that were implemented during this period. The thesis will ask why these acts were implemented, what impact they had on the health of textile workers, and what were the wider ramifications that this legislation had for industry in the city.

BA in History. University College Dublin

I hold a BA (Honours) (International) in History from University College Dublin. The single major 'Mode 1' history program at UCD is aimed at preparing students for postgraduate study and as such incorporates many of the skills required at the postgraduate level into its classes, such as primary research skills, critical thinking, and dissertation writing. An integral component of the program was the writing of a 10,000 word research-based dissertation. The topic for this project was at the discretion of the student in consultation with an academic advisor, and the emphasis of the project was centred around individual archival research and independent study. My dissertation looked at friendly societies in early 20th Century Belfast, a period when the city had experienced rapid industrialisation, becoming Ireland's largest city and one of Britain's most important industrial centres. More specifically, it is a study of the gendered nature of these societies, exploring differences and disparities that existed between societies with male and female memberships in terms of their functions and their objectives. It argues that those societies which had a female membership placed more of an emphasis on the 'purification' of their members, and therefore pursued a much more moralistic agenda than their male counterparts. This led to the physical and financial welfare of the female members being neglected in favour of moral welfare, while the more industrially-linked male societies did more to protect their members. More broadly, the paper addresses the differing attitudes towards men and women in early 20th Century Belfast. The topic of this project is unique in the historiography of Belfast and Ireland as a whole, and as such is based almost entirely in new primary research.

Boston College- Exchange Year 2013-14

The third year of my degree was spent studying at Boston College as part of an academic exchange program. During this time I was able to familiarize myself with the American academic system, as well as studying an even wider range of fields within history and in other disciplines. The year provided me with a different perspective on many issues, and has allowed me to take a much more rounded, holistic approach to history. The range of techniques, assessments, and perspectives that I experienced during my time at Boston College have added another important dimension to my education, and have given me a new perspective with which I now view academic study.

Furthermore, the year has greatly contributed to my decision to pursue graduate study in the United States, and further fuelled my desire to forge a career in history.

WORK EXPERIENCE:

May 2014- August 2016 Wine Waiter, Sleepy Hollow Restaurant, Newtownabbey

May 2013 – September 2013 Team member, Titanic Museum Belfast

May 2012-September 2012 Food Service Assistant, Fed & Watered, Belfast

International Airport